<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Igor Kostyuchenok</title>
  
  <subtitle>Igor&#39;s Blog</subtitle>
  <link href="https://kostyuchenok.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="https://kostyuchenok.com/"/>
  <updated>2024-02-06T16:28:20.213Z</updated>
  <id>https://kostyuchenok.com/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Igor Kostyuchenok</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="https://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Self Sabotage</title>
    <link href="https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2024/02/01/self-sabotage/"/>
    <id>https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2024/02/01/self-sabotage/</id>
    <published>2024-02-01T13:31:05.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-06T16:28:20.213Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>This post is a mix of the ideas taken out of the Netflix movie <a href="https://www.netflix.com/tudum/stutz">Stutz</a> and my own knowledge on psychology, evolution and creativity gathered over the years.</p></blockquote><p>The first step to overcome our brain’s intention to self sabotage important decisions is to embrace the reality. There are three aspects of the reality that no one can avoid. Those three aspects are:</p><ul><li>Pain - no matter what you do in life, no matter how good your intentions are - the pain is inevitable</li><li>Uncertainty - even if you try to thoroughly plan every step you take and every thought you think, there will always be stuff out of your control. It will have an impact on you - either positive or negative but you won’t be able to control it</li><li>Constant Work - work on yourself never stops. Whenever you think you are it means you start going backwards</li></ul><span id="more"></span><p>So, what is the origin of <code>Self Sabotage</code>. We humans have been living in a rather safe environment for the last couple of hundreds of years. Before that for thousands of year we lived in a state of constant danger, which lead to our brain developing the protection mechanism against everything that it sees as a danger.</p><p>Although the intentional idea has been very good and helped us to survive all this thousands of years as a species, we need to overcome this protection whenever we have to develop a new habit. See the <code>Self Sabotage</code> as your <code>comfort zone</code> that actively holds you back from any changes - negative or positive ones.</p><p><code>Self Sabotage</code> is coming from the primal part of our brains and cannot be avoided. There is no known way to switch it off, whenever there will be uncertainty there will be self-doubt. The greater the uncertainty and adversity the bigger the opportunity and the more your brain will try to sabotage it.</p><p>If you can learn to overcome your fears, it will change your life. Let’s examine some of the tools that can be helpful in overcoming <code>Self Sabotage</code>.</p><p>The shame and embarrassment is the glue that holds the humanity together. We were created to make mistakes. Making mistakes is the only way to accomplishing anything in life.</p><h1 id="The-Tools"><a href="#The-Tools" class="headerlink" title="The Tools"></a>The Tools</h1><p>The Tools are a set of exercises that can help you to turn an unpleasant experience into an opportunity.</p><h2 id="String-of-Pearls"><a href="#String-of-Pearls" class="headerlink" title="String of Pearls"></a>String of Pearls</h2><p>Don’t devalue the small steps you’re taking. Even the smallest ones. Doing every small thing the best as you can, will definitely yield results.</p><p>Imagine your life as a string of pearls. Every pearl is one action. Every action has the same value.It doesn’t matter where an action is a failure or a success - the most important thing is to keep going and put the next pearl on the string.</p><p>You got out of bed - you just put a pearl on your string. You brushed your teeth - boom - next pearl is on the string. You wrote one sentence of your new book - there is your next pearl etc. etc.</p><p>As we already learned <code>uncertainty</code> is one of the three aspects of reality we cannot avoid. The winner is someone, who keeps putting pearls on his string ignoring the uncertainty and pain.</p><blockquote><p>The true confidence is living in uncertainty and moving forward. – Dr. Phil Stutz</p></blockquote><p>Every pearl on the string will have an imperfection inside and that’s ok. Perfection kills productivity and can even kill the best intentions. Do the best you can right now and keep going.</p><h2 id="The-Shadow"><a href="#The-Shadow" class="headerlink" title="The Shadow"></a>The Shadow</h2><p>The Shadow represents the part of yourself you’re ashamed of - the time when you were fat or the time when you were skinny, the time when you chickened out or the time when you were extremely indecisive. But all these times in the past it was also you. This part of you won’t to be recognized as well.</p><p>As long as you will try to avoid confronting your past, imperfect self - you won’t be at peace with it and it will appear at the most inconvenient times and block you again. Recognize yourself, be at peace with yourself and the next decision you must make will fall easier.</p><h2 id="The-Snapshot"><a href="#The-Snapshot" class="headerlink" title="The Snapshot"></a>The Snapshot</h2><p>The world is not perfect and neither are we. Understanding all that our brain is still able to trick us into the illusion of the perfect experience. We are searching for it even knowing that it doesn’t exist. The perfection only exists in our mind. It’s not to be found in the real world.</p><p>No matter whether you’re looking for a perfect partner or a perfect movie - you are destined to fail. There will be nearly perfect moments in your life - no doubt about it but these will be just moments - the snapshots. The snapshot is a still picture. It has no depth - the depth is added by the imperfections. We are chasing the perfection that doesn’t exist ignoring three aspects of reality - pain, uncertainty and constant work.</p><p>Money and success won’t remove three aspects of reality. Stop chasing the phantom and start living.</p><h2 id="The-Maze"><a href="#The-Maze" class="headerlink" title="The Maze"></a>The Maze</h2><p>The Maze is the by-product of <code>Self Sabotage</code> because <code>Self Sabotage</code> wants <code>fairness</code>. A classic example of the maze is when you spend lots of time talking about someone who mistreated you in the past. You’re looking for fairness but at the same time the endless search for fairness blocks you from moving forward. It blocks you from taking the next step because you’re afraid that you will get treated unfair again.</p><blockquote><p>Request for fairness puts your life on hold. – Dr. Phil Stutz</p></blockquote>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is a mix of the ideas taken out of the Netflix movie &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netflix.com/tudum/stutz&quot;&gt;Stutz&lt;/a&gt; and my own knowledge on psychology, evolution and creativity gathered over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step to overcome our brain’s intention to self sabotage important decisions is to embrace the reality. There are three aspects of the reality that no one can avoid. Those three aspects are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pain - no matter what you do in life, no matter how good your intentions are - the pain is inevitable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uncertainty - even if you try to thoroughly plan every step you take and every thought you think, there will always be stuff out of your control. It will have an impact on you - either positive or negative but you won’t be able to control it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Constant Work - work on yourself never stops. Whenever you think you are it means you start going backwards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="psychology, mentoring, part x, self sabotage" scheme="https://kostyuchenok.com/tags/psychology-mentoring-part-x-self-sabotage/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Life Force</title>
    <link href="https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2024/01/29/life-force/"/>
    <id>https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2024/01/29/life-force/</id>
    <published>2024-01-29T08:21:51.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-06T16:28:20.209Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Each man had only one genuine vocation - to find the way to himself….His task was to discover his own destiny - not an arbitrary one - and to live it out wholly and resolutely within himself. Everything else was only a would-be existence, an attempt at evasion, a flight back to the ideals of the masses, conformity and fear of one’s own inwardness.<br>― Herman Hesse</p></blockquote><span id="more"></span><p>If you had troubles finding your vocation, it may be due to the fact that you’re out of your life force. Let’s see what the life force is and how you can get it back.</p><p>If you feel down and depressed. If you feel like you lost a sense of direction and you don’t know what to do next. You can always work on your life force.</p><p>The only way to find our what you should be doing or who you truly are is to activate your life force. Life force is the only part of you that is capable of guiding you when you’re lost.</p><p>If you imagine a life force being a pyramid, there are three levels of it:</p><ul><li>The bottom level, the foundation is <code>your relationship with your physical body</code>.</li><li>The second level is <code>your relationship with other people</code>.</li><li>The highest level is <code>your relationship with yourself</code>.</li></ul><p><img src="/blog/2024/01/29/life-force/Life-Force-Triangle.png" alt="Life Force Triangle"></p><h1 id="Body"><a href="#Body" class="headerlink" title="Body"></a>Body</h1><p>That is the bottom step of the life force.</p><p>You have to take care of your  body first. Otherwise you cannot take on any serious task in your life. Your judgments will be compromised by your health issues.</p><p>Your objective is to get your body working better and it always works. The most classic thing why your body is not at its best, is the lack of <code>exercise</code>.</p><p>The second most important thing is your <code>diet</code>. And the third one is your <code>sleep</code>.</p><p>So, when you start taking care of your body you will automatically start feeling better. In the very beginning improving your relationship with your body will give you 85% of your life force.</p><ul><li>Exercise</li><li>Diet</li><li>Sleep</li></ul><p>Your relationship with your body is only the first level. The next level is <code>your relationship with other people</code>.</p><h1 id="People"><a href="#People" class="headerlink" title="People"></a>People</h1><p>When you’re getting depressed you not necessarily end your relationship with other people but they are more and more getting pulled back from your life.</p><p>The relationships are like steps in a ladder. The more of them disappear from your life the harder it will get to climb up the ladder, cause the steps are missing. Without steps it will get harder and harder to pull yourself back into life.</p><p>They key here is - you have to take the initiative. You shouldn’t be waiting for other people to take the initiative. If you wait for them to do it, you don’t understand the problem.</p><p>You have to be proactive in meeting new people and communicate with them.</p><p>You could invite someone to lunch that you don’t find interesting. It doesn’t really matter. It will still affect you in a positive way. Every person you interact with symbolically represents the whole humanity.</p><p>That’s the middle tier. The highest tier though is <code>your relationship with yourself</code>.</p><h1 id="Yourself"><a href="#Yourself" class="headerlink" title="Yourself"></a>Yourself</h1><p>That is the highest tier in your <code>Life Force Triangle</code>.</p><p>Your relationship with yourself is to be understood as <code>your relationship with your unconscious</code>. You don’t really know what’s in your unconscious, until you activate it.</p><p>One trick that you can use is <code>writing</code>. Writing is a magical thing that activate your unconscious.</p><p>Your get to know yourself by writing. It doesn’t matter what you write. You don’t have to be a writer. If you just start writing, it will act as a mirror. Your writing will reflect, what’s going on in your unconscious and things that you didn’t that you knew, will start coming out.</p><p>These are the three pillars of your life force. If you feel lost, don’t try to figure it out - work on you life force first and things will fall into place.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each man had only one genuine vocation - to find the way to himself….His task was to discover his own destiny - not an arbitrary one - and to live it out wholly and resolutely within himself. Everything else was only a would-be existence, an attempt at evasion, a flight back to the ideals of the masses, conformity and fear of one’s own inwardness.&lt;br&gt;― Herman Hesse&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="mentorship, coaching, life, vocation" scheme="https://kostyuchenok.com/tags/mentorship-coaching-life-vocation/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Own Nothing</title>
    <link href="https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2024/01/07/own-nothing/"/>
    <id>https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2024/01/07/own-nothing/</id>
    <published>2024-01-07T17:21:46.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-06T16:28:20.213Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We’ve been hearing the <code>declutter</code>, <code>shared economy</code> and <code>own less</code> to <code>own nothing</code> narrative for the past couple of years now but what is it all about? Why, all of a sudden, we should stop owning anything although it is against our nature. Why is this narrative being pushed upon us so vigorously by the people that are owning almost everything? Let’s find out.</p><span id="more"></span><p>Just 60-70 years ago, owning a home, a couple of cars and a business was a dream of at least 90% of the people. And that’s not a surprise really. Since forever people have been trying to get independent by building its wealth and getting a certain societal status.</p><p>We, people, are social animals and the status game is one of the few games that’s hard-coded in us. We’ve been playing it since tribal times and we’ve been loving it. It’s not a surprise, since we’re wired for hierarchy and the status game.</p><p>How did it come to be that many people have bought into the <code>own nothing</code> narrative, assuming it’s actually against people’s nature?</p><p>Let’s analyze who’s interested in the majority that does neither own a car nor a house. Whoever will rent both of those properties out to you - your landlord or a car rental company. Despite the fact that the idea is sold to you as being liberating it is actually limiting. You may think you have all the choices in the world - live anywhere you like and drive any car you want but it could also mean - <code>you can only live where you&#39;re allowed to or only drive a car that is rented out to you</code> and both those choices are not necessarily your decisions. You landlord decides whether you will be able to rent a house of a flat and the car owner will decide, whether you will be allowed to drive a rental.</p><p>On top of that you’re getting accustomed to letting go of any of your possessions. It teaches you not to protect what’s yours and be <code>ok</code> with what you already have (which is not too bad in first approximation and sounds rather stoic) but it also teaches you not to strive for anything, lower your expectations and just become more obedient than you already are.</p><p>Without owning anything you can end up on the street very easily - you’re unprotected. If a rental company or an individual want to block you from renting their stuff - they can and you cannot do anything about it - you don’t own it.</p><p>If you have already bought into the idea of owning nothing, you’re already being controlled. Someone incepted this idea into your mind against your will, against the human nature.</p><p>Always remember that people who are convincing you to get rid of all of your possessions are the ones who own multiple real estates, multiple cars and will gladly rent them out to you as long as you don’t misbehave.</p><p>If you have bought into this story telling, here is your 3 step plan for you to become a perfect citizen:</p><ul><li>Own nothing</li><li>Decide nothing</li><li>Be nothing</li></ul>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We’ve been hearing the &lt;code&gt;declutter&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;shared economy&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;own less&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;own nothing&lt;/code&gt; narrative for the past couple of years now but what is it all about? Why, all of a sudden, we should stop owning anything although it is against our nature. Why is this narrative being pushed upon us so vigorously by the people that are owning almost everything? Let’s find out.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="shared, economy, nothing, ownership, narrative, false" scheme="https://kostyuchenok.com/tags/shared-economy-nothing-ownership-narrative-false/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Rich People Economy</title>
    <link href="https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2023/11/30/rich-people-economy/"/>
    <id>https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2023/11/30/rich-people-economy/</id>
    <published>2023-11-30T16:15:22.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-06T16:28:20.213Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you have ever asked yourself why rich people get richer and poor people get poorer - this article is for you</p><p>Let’s see why it is so hard to leave the poverty land and acquire the rich people mentality.</p><p>To fully understand the problem, let’s illustrate the differences between a person being born into a wealthy family versus a person being born into a regular one.</p><span id="more"></span><p>Being born into a wealthy family comes with a lot of perks. From the very childhood you have the access to the best possible education. As a child you will have a private tutor teaching you different language and giving you history and geography lessons, so once you reach the school age you will already have a superior view on the world, as the normal kids.</p><p>Once you reach the school age, you will attend the best possible private educational institution with other smart and reach kids, making valuable connections from the very early age. Even if you are not very smart or if you are lazy, by finishing the school you will have built up a great network of high network individuals and future company executives and political leaders.</p><p>After you finished your school, you will attend one of the best universities in the world and will continue extending your network and once you will get out of the door of your high profile educational facility you are set for the rest of your life - you have the most extended connection grid consisting of your schoolmates, university mates and their parents. You will automatically land a high-paying job without the need of having any experience or the need to prove that you are worth of it.</p><p>In contrary to that, if you were born in a regular family, at the end of your school you will have received a mediocre education and surrounded yourself mainly with regular people. Only 5% of them will achieve anything in their lifetime. You are automatically excluded from the network of power and wealth.</p><p>You will attend a regular university, earning a mediocre degree and struggling to get a job because you won’t have received any valuable experience during your studies. Once you will land a job in a bigger company or a large corporation, you will start wondering: <code>why don&#39;t many of your bosses understand the business they are in and why they are never responsible for the mistakes they make</code>.</p><p>It’s a regular practice to not fire a CEO even if she made a huge mistake that caused a company huge losses. Most of the time the responsibility is pushed on to the higher management with the explanation <code>they weren&#39;t able to execute the orders of the CEO/CTO/CFO etc.</code>. Even in an unlikely event of the head of the company being fired, she will be immediately offered a new high paying position at another high profile company.</p><p>Having the largest network of high network individuals, a rich person will be offered a lot of luxury goods for free. As a regular person, you will look up to a successful person. You will try to copy her way of life thinking that by owning luxury things, you will be part of the network but don’t kid yourself you never will.</p><p>Even if you have reached high status and became truly wealthy, you will always be looked down upon by a person being born into a rich family.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you have ever asked yourself why rich people get richer and poor people get poorer - this article is for you&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s see why it is so hard to leave the poverty land and acquire the rich people mentality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To fully understand the problem, let’s illustrate the differences between a person being born into a wealthy family versus a person being born into a regular one.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Reverse Pitch</title>
    <link href="https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2023/10/06/reverse-pitch/"/>
    <id>https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2023/10/06/reverse-pitch/</id>
    <published>2023-10-06T16:37:59.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-06T16:28:20.213Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Best way to get invested in is <code>not to ask for money</code>.</p><p>If you want to secure an investment from a reputable investor or a VC fund you have to use the <code>reverse pitch</code> method</p><span id="more"></span><p>What is a <code>reverse pitch</code>. As you may have already guessed it’s when an investor pitches himself to you.</p><p>How do you get an investor pitching to you though?</p><p>What you have to understand in the first place is that an investor gets thousands of pitches a year and only places 1 to 2 investments. Even if you will get 15-30 minutes to pitch your product, the most investment decisions are done in the first 2 minutes, so you have only 2 minutes to catch your potential investor’s attention.</p><p>If you will start as any other startup presenting your product and begging for money, you already lost the game even if you have an incredible product. Here where the <code>reverse pitch</code> comes into play.</p><p>Here are the steps that need to be taken in order to achieve the situation where an investor pitches herself to you:</p><ul><li>Do a thorough research on the investors and find the ones who already invested in similart startups or in the startups in similar categories.</li><li>Although you won’t really pitch your product, you have to know it really well. Know you market, know your reach. Be solid when you spit facts and be confident about your success.</li><li>Once you’ve done all the preparations, talk to the investors of your choice, briefly introduce your company or product and ask them how they can help you to reach your goals. Don’t ask for money but ask them if they have enough connections and expertise to help your company grow exponentially.</li></ul><p>They will get definitely more intrigued by your approach then by a standard pitch deck - they’ve already seen thousands of them and you will have way better chances to get to the next step.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Best way to get invested in is &lt;code&gt;not to ask for money&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to secure an investment from a reputable investor or a VC fund you have to use the &lt;code&gt;reverse pitch&lt;/code&gt; method&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Exaltatio</title>
    <link href="https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2023/06/13/exaltatio/"/>
    <id>https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2023/06/13/exaltatio/</id>
    <published>2023-06-13T20:40:22.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-06T16:28:20.205Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><code>Exaltatio</code> - Latin for <code>a state of being carried away by overwhelming emotion</code></p><p><code>May you live in interesting times</code> - English curse</p><span id="more"></span><p>If you are not excited about the future, then you must be deeply depressed about it.</p><p>The world is in the turmoil. It always is but now all the world starts to feel it. We are amidst of the big change that will either end the unipolar world or establish it even stronger.</p><p>In case of any outcome everyone in the world will feel it big time. If you believe in the fairy tale of evil Russia trying to rob Ukraine of its independence - stop reading right now and go and do some research finally.</p><p>The battle we’re all witnessing at the moment is the battle for keeping the West at its power. That’s the battle that US is fighting with Ukrainian hands and the European money.</p><p>The west is losing the <code>free market</code> competition. The east is on the rise and neither Europe nor USA can compete with them without the unfair advantage of having access to cheap resources.</p><p>As we all remember Josep Borrell was talking about it during the <a href="https://www.eeas.europa.eu/eeas/eu-ambassadors-annual-conference-2022-opening-speech-high-representative-josep-borrell_en">EU Ambassadors Annual Conference 2022</a>:</p><blockquote><p>Our prosperity has been based on cheap energy coming from Russia. Russian gas – cheap and supposedly affordable, secure, and stable.</p></blockquote><p>So, US made sure that Europe doesn’t have access to cheap resources anymore by blowing up the Nord-Stream-Pipelines and not leaving Europeans any chance to not participate in the currently running conflict by providing financial and military aid to Ukraine.</p><p>Europe is on the US hook and cannot say anything against its <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suzerainty">suzerain</a>. If it would, then the financial decline would come way faster that it will.</p><p>Europe took the lesser of two evils with the hope of experiencing the collapse of Russian Federation as a multi national state just to later get the needed resources almost for free.</p><p>The current military conflict is the one between the weakening super power and its mignons against the <code>developing</code> and the <code>3rd</code> world that is sick and tired of being oppressed and robbed by the friendly and educated Europeans and Americans. To illustrate what the <code>golden billion</code> thinks about the rest of the world, let’s use the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f8SKblpc7kY">speech</a> of already mentioned in this blog post Josep Borrell:</p><blockquote><p>Europe is a garden. We have built a garden…The rest of the world – and you know this very well, Federica [Mogherini] – is not exactly a garden. Most of the rest of the world is a jungle, and the jungle could invade the garden.</p></blockquote><p>You’re not welcome in the sacred garden that was build by using cheap or even free resources probably from the  country you’re coming from.</p><p>Russian politicians are aware of that along with the Russian people, thus they will fight until the very end. It’s their battle for survival, whereas for the West it’s the battle to stay on top of the food chain.</p><p>Let’s discuss the potential outcomes of the current conflict between the West and the East. The one thing we know for sure, the world will get less global than it is right now.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Exaltatio&lt;/code&gt; - Latin for &lt;code&gt;a state of being carried away by overwhelming emotion&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;May you live in interesting times&lt;/code&gt; - English curse&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Progression</title>
    <link href="https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2023/02/27/progression/"/>
    <id>https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2023/02/27/progression/</id>
    <published>2023-02-27T09:49:10.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-06T16:28:20.213Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you want your team to be efficient, you will have to nurture and grow your own talent. It may be very seductive to hire an on- or an off-shore software development shop to quickly build out your product but it’s a slippery slope if you are planning to build a proper company and not just ride the hype wave and hope you will sell out soon.</p><span id="more"></span><p>Let’s see what are the advantages of an external team:</p><ul><li>You don’t have to deal with finding, hiring and teaching people</li><li>You don’t have to inspire and manage them</li></ul><p>What are the disadvantages:</p><ul><li>The external team will never buy in into your idea</li><li>You won’t be able to motivate them</li><li>You will never be in full control of the product that’s being built</li></ul><p>For people to progress quicker they must feel safe. In order to create a safe environment, you have to be transparent with them - transparent about the company, the product, your plans and their career path.</p><p>The career path transparency may be the most crucial part of the safety equation.</p><h2 id="Team-Dynamics"><a href="#Team-Dynamics" class="headerlink" title="Team Dynamics"></a>Team Dynamics</h2><p>A-Players don’t want to work with B-Players and may even leave your company if some B-Players will sneak in. The main problem with the B-Players is their insecurity. They will do everything to hire people who are less smart than them, what can cause a complete deterioration of the company.</p><p>A team of A-Players will work as a well-oiled machine. Adding a B-Player to it is like throwing a stone into the working engine. The engine will slow down at first, start rattling at second and break at last.</p><h2 id="Productivity"><a href="#Productivity" class="headerlink" title="Productivity"></a>Productivity</h2><p>Different people thrive in different environments. Some people work better in a totally relaxed atmosphere whereas the others are more productive under pressure.</p><p>Having different personalities on the team will help you keep your productivity high at all times.</p><h2 id="Growing-Talent"><a href="#Growing-Talent" class="headerlink" title="Growing Talent"></a>Growing Talent</h2><p>Growing your own talent may be rewarding but it’s also very costly. Sometimes it’s unavoidable though.</p><p>If you’re building your new team and bootstrapping you won’t have enough money to hire the senior people you may need. Growing your own talent is one possible way to go.</p><p>Advantages of growing your own talent:</p><ul><li>You will be able to grow talent that breathes your culture</li><li>They will grow together with your company and have an emotional bond to it</li><li>They will not just work for money but feel as part of the family</li></ul><p>Disadvantages of growing your own talent:</p><ul><li>It takes time</li><li>It’s rather expensive</li><li>The inexperienced people will inevitable <code>waste</code> the time of your more experienced team members</li><li>They won’t immediately contribute to the success of your company</li><li>Some people may leave your company immediately after they started to get some knowledge. You have to think about smart ways to incentivise them to stay</li></ul><h2 id="Progression-Framework"><a href="#Progression-Framework" class="headerlink" title="Progression Framework"></a>Progression Framework</h2><p>As we already stated above to create a safe environment, where people can grow professionally and personally, we need to establish a clear growth path that people can follow to get to new heights of their careers.</p><p>This <code>progression framework</code> has to outline the work that has to be performed and knowledge that has to be gained to get to the next steps in our career.</p><p>Your <code>progression framework</code> has to be supported by the day-to-day work and the tasks that are assigned to your junior team members by the senior ones. Their progression has to be tracked and aligned. Otherwise you will run into the misunderstandings of expectations and won’t be able to properly measure the performance of your team members.</p><p>You have to set and track both short-, mid- and long-term goals for your team members and thus perform short-, mid- and long-term performance reviews and interviews with them. Use the weekly one-on-ones, monthly and quarterly performance reviews. The weekly one-on-ones are mainly for your team member to ask questions, raise concerns and propose improvements.</p><p>During the monthly and quarterly reviews, your senior team members should not only provide the feedback on the current state of the progression but also outline the steps that has to be taken to continue to progress successfully or get back on track if the progression has been derailed. They also have to reevaluate and potentially to set new goals that have to be achieved until the next performance review.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you want your team to be efficient, you will have to nurture and grow your own talent. It may be very seductive to hire an on- or an off-shore software development shop to quickly build out your product but it’s a slippery slope if you are planning to build a proper company and not just ride the hype wave and hope you will sell out soon.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="startup, team, management" scheme="https://kostyuchenok.com/tags/startup-team-management/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Hire Please</title>
    <link href="https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2023/02/16/hire-please/"/>
    <id>https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2023/02/16/hire-please/</id>
    <published>2023-02-16T15:21:15.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-06T16:28:20.209Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Everything written below is highly influenced by my personal experience and talks that were given by the people I’m following.</p><span id="more"></span><div style="text-align: center;">  <figure>    <img width="100%" src="hire-please.jpeg"/>    <figcaption>      Teams of Startup Founders    </figcaption>  </figure></div><h2 id="Protect-Your-Team"><a href="#Protect-Your-Team" class="headerlink" title="Protect Your Team"></a>Protect Your Team</h2><p>A good leader always protects his team from other teams and other leaders (higher management).</p><ul><li>A failure of your team is your failure</li><li>A success of your team is their success</li></ul><h2 id="Support-Your-Team"><a href="#Support-Your-Team" class="headerlink" title="Support Your Team"></a>Support Your Team</h2><p>What to do when one of your teammates decided to leave - support her, even if it’s hard for you. When you see that people cannot grow further in your company or in their position, if you cannot give them the chance to grow - support them, even encourage them to leave. You’ll get a loyal person in another company/team.</p><h2 id="Loyalty"><a href="#Loyalty" class="headerlink" title="Loyalty"></a>Loyalty</h2><p>Don’t expect people to be loyal to your brand. People should be loyal to the team they belong to, not to the brand.</p><h2 id="Same-Values"><a href="#Same-Values" class="headerlink" title="Same Values"></a>Same Values</h2><p>The team and the leader should share the same values. Whenever you hire a new team member you should find out what she is ready for and what she’s not.<br>Try to hire people, not robots. The people who leave the workplace at 6pm sharp regardless of the current situation at work are as bad as the ones who put work before their kids or family.</p><h2 id="Behavioral-Patterns"><a href="#Behavioral-Patterns" class="headerlink" title="Behavioral Patterns"></a>Behavioral Patterns</h2><p>People don’t change. They also behave the same at work as they do with their family. See how your teammates behave. If your teammate treats his family badly the same will happen at work. Don’t kid yourself.</p><h2 id="Inspiration"><a href="#Inspiration" class="headerlink" title="Inspiration"></a>Inspiration</h2><p>You cannot inspire people. Your goal should be to hire inspired people. If you hire the ones who love what they do, they’ll already be inspired by themselves. The best thing you can do is to to not kill their inspiration.<br>Communicate honestly with them. They should know why do you think they shouldn’t do certain things. But bear in mind if you already tried something and failed it doesn’t necessarily mean it won’t work next time with different people.</p><h2 id="Let-Them-Make-Mistakes"><a href="#Let-Them-Make-Mistakes" class="headerlink" title="Let Them Make Mistakes"></a>Let Them Make Mistakes</h2><p>You have to let them make their own mistakes. Mistakes are the best source of learning - that’s just a nature of learing. If you make all the decisions for them they won’t grow and will leave sooner rather than later. If you let them make their own mistakes they will grow faster by order of magnitude.</p><h2 id="Let-Them-Show-Off"><a href="#Let-Them-Show-Off" class="headerlink" title="Let Them Show Off"></a>Let Them Show Off</h2><p>Let your people the chance to show their accomplishments. If you see a team where only the leader is known for the work done, it means he is afraid of growing people stronger than him. A leader has to be sure that when he quit there are two people who can take his place and work better than him.</p><h2 id="Listen"><a href="#Listen" class="headerlink" title="Listen"></a>Listen</h2><p>Whenever you have to make a decision, hear everyone’s opinion before you announce your own. If you announce your opinion/solution first and hear a better one afterwards, it might get hard for you to accept it. It can lead to an irrational decision just because your pride didn’t let you take someone else’s opinion before yours.</p><h2 id="Gossip"><a href="#Gossip" class="headerlink" title="Gossip"></a>Gossip</h2><p>Don’t allow or participate in any gossip inside of your team - it will tear your team apart. Even worse, when you have a confrontation between two strong personalities inside of your team - you’ll have to fire at least one of them.</p><h2 id="Firing"><a href="#Firing" class="headerlink" title="Firing"></a>Firing</h2><p>Contrary to a popular believe, firing people is at least if not even more important than hiring them. You will make hiring mistakes, there’s no way around it. Sometimes you will hire people because you really liked them and were enamored by them. Some of those hires will work out, others won’t.</p><p>Once you realized you made a wrong hire, do not hesitate to part ways with this person. You’re the person in charge now. Nobody else will do it for you. Yes, it sucks to bring bad news to people but the longer you hesitate the harder it will get and the more damage your company will experience.</p><p>The outperformers on your team are the ones you should take care of in the first place and they will definitely see wrong hires. If you don’t correct your mistakes you can start bleeding people that move your company forward.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Everything written below is highly influenced by my personal experience and talks that were given by the people I’m following.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="hire, fire, people, management, team" scheme="https://kostyuchenok.com/tags/hire-fire-people-management-team/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Founding Team</title>
    <link href="https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2023/02/16/founders/"/>
    <id>https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2023/02/16/founders/</id>
    <published>2023-02-16T14:27:45.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-06T16:28:20.205Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you’re long enough in the tech business, you should have heard a tale about 3H that every startup needs. In order for a startup to become successful it needs 3 founders:</p><ul><li>a Hacker</li><li>a Hustler</li><li>a Hippie (they call it Hipster nowadays but don’t follow the crowd)</li></ul><span id="more"></span><div style="text-align: center;">  <figure>    <img width="100%" src="founders.jpeg"/>    <figcaption>      Mbanq Founders at the Mbanq Labs Hackathon in Singapore    </figcaption>  </figure></div><p>If you think about this setup for a bit, this constellation will definitely start making sense.</p><p>Let’s see what every one of those <code>3H</code> actually entails.</p><h2 id="A-Hacker"><a href="#A-Hacker" class="headerlink" title="A Hacker"></a>A Hacker</h2><p>Let’s start with the easiest one. A Hacker is your CTO - someone who will build the product, someone who cares about building cool products, someone who understands how to spend time efficiently.</p><p>Some tend to spend too much time over optimizing the early stage product.<br>Scalability doesn’t matter when you didn’t find your product fit yet. When you over optimize too early in the process, you’re wasting at least double the time by not executing on your idea, losing time on unnecessary bells and whistles before having found your product market fit.</p><p>As you may know, startup is all about the execution. The faster you can execute, the higher are the chances of your startup to become successful.</p><p>So a hacker should know how to <code>cut corners</code> in a smart way. There is a huge difference between your <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minimum_viable_product">MVP</a> and your end product.</p><p>Building products is hard, building valuable products is even harder - that’s exactly why every <code>hacker</code> needs a counterpart - <code>a hippie</code>.</p><h2 id="A-Hippie"><a href="#A-Hippie" class="headerlink" title="A Hippie"></a>A Hippie</h2><p>Who’s a hippie you may ask. If you are too young and don’t know who <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Jobs">Steve<br>Jobs</a> was, I pity you and recommend you to start getting to know about him.</p><p>Up to this date, I personally consider him to be the best <code>product person</code><br>ever - you can argue, I don’t care.</p><p>So, if you haven’t seen <a href="https://vimeo.com/475108226">The Lost Interview</a> yet - do it now, you won’t regret it.</p><p>One of the questions Steve was asked is <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uf6TzOHO_dk">Are you a hippie or a nerd</a> - so when the best <code>product person</code> of all time considered himself <code>a hippie</code>, we can assume that <code>a hippie</code> is your <code>CPO</code>.</p><h2 id="A-Hustler"><a href="#A-Hustler" class="headerlink" title="A Hustler"></a>A Hustler</h2><p>This one is almost as clear as <code>a hacker</code> position. Your hustler is your <code>Head of Sales</code>. A very important person on your team. Don’t be disillusioned - <a href="https://samuelmullen.com/articles/startup-fallacies-if-you-build-it-they-will-come/">build it and they will come</a> is a fallacy. In the world full of similar products and never ending competition, you need <code>a hustler</code> who will sell your product to your customers and your idea to the investors.</p><p>This is the person who knows and believes in your product and help <code>a hippie</code> to find the best possible <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Product/market_fit">Product/market fit</a>.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you’re long enough in the tech business, you should have heard a tale about 3H that every startup needs. In order for a startup to become successful it needs 3 founders:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a Hacker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a Hustler&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a Hippie (they call it Hipster nowadays but don’t follow the crowd)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="startup, founders, team, founding team" scheme="https://kostyuchenok.com/tags/startup-founders-team-founding-team/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Sell Please</title>
    <link href="https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2023/02/05/sell-please/"/>
    <id>https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2023/02/05/sell-please/</id>
    <published>2023-02-05T16:04:19.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-06T16:28:20.213Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>First thing you have to understand is <code>the products don&#39;t sell themselves</code>. Build it and they will come - never works.<br>You will have to do marketing for your product or service.</p><p>If you want to successfully sell your product or service, you should sell a story.</p><span id="more"></span><div style="text-align: center;">  <figure>    <img width="100%" src="sell-please.jpeg"/>    <figcaption>      Singapore Business District    </figcaption>  </figure></div><p>People are egocentric, social creatures who value their status in society. Every product that contributes to their value will get high attention. This way products can move from being used to solving problems to becoming status symbols: <code>Rolex</code>, <code>iPhone</code>, <code>Tesla</code>. The products that moved into the <code>status symbol</code> category will yield the highest earnings for the product provider.</p><p>It’s not the only <code>status symbol</code> category that needs to sell a story though. Ultimately every product should. You don’t sell flight tickets - you sell freedom to travel. You don’t sell the possibility to book an apartment or a hotel, you sell the dream of being local in a new place or to live a luxurious life for 3 days a year etc. etc.</p><p>If you think this pattern is only applicable for the consumer products, you are wrong. Absolutely the same is true for the <code>B2B</code> sector. Every company wants to be better than its competitors and they are ready to pay the premium price if you will sell your product the right way.</p><p>In order to sell your product, you have to truly know your customer and push the right buttons</p><p>Build up a loyal community of early adopters - people who trust you, will do the early tests of your product and give you an honest feedback you can use to improve your product or service. Offer your early adopters community special deals on you products or services - nurture and engage with your community.</p><p>Selling a product is as important as building it. You not only have to sell your product to your customers but you often you have to sell it to your investor as well. Thus your <code>Head of Sales</code> has to both know your product in and out and believe in your idea and support it fully.</p><h1 id="Gist"><a href="#Gist" class="headerlink" title="Gist"></a>Gist</h1><ul><li>You sell a story not a product or service</li><li>Product as a status symbol will yield more revenue</li><li>Build a loyal customer community. They will help you to grow your customer base (see <code>Apple</code>, <code>Tesla</code>)</li><li>Learn to sell your idea both to your customers and your investors</li></ul>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;First thing you have to understand is &lt;code&gt;the products don&amp;#39;t sell themselves&lt;/code&gt;. Build it and they will come - never works.&lt;br&gt;You will have to do marketing for your product or service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to successfully sell your product or service, you should sell a story.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="marketing, sales, sell, selling, product" scheme="https://kostyuchenok.com/tags/marketing-sales-sell-selling-product/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Funding Please</title>
    <link href="https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2023/01/31/funding-please/"/>
    <id>https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2023/01/31/funding-please/</id>
    <published>2023-01-31T14:45:54.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-06T16:28:20.209Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I was setting up the Mbanq Labs accelerator in Singapore, I had a chance to talk to many founders and consult a lot of startups.</p><p>What was striking to me, besides their eagerness to build their products, is how hard it was for them to clearly articulate the idea of their product in one sentence.</p><span id="more"></span><div style="text-align: center;">  <figure>    <img width="100%" src="funding-please.jpeg"/>    <figcaption>      Daniel Ong giving a speech in front of startup founders    </figcaption>  </figure></div><p>Startups are all about the speed of execution and iteration. If you don’t have enough financial resources to hire a team to execute on your idea 24/7 for the next 3-6 months, your best bet is to find like-minded people and start working on your pitch-deck.</p><p>Do not see your pitch-deck as <code>a means to an end</code> but rather as en exercise that you will have to do every couple of months to review your product and its position on the market. You’re doing this work primarily for yourself and not for a potential investor. You need it more than anyone else.</p><p>It’s not about you having a detailed execution plan, cause assuming that<br>everything will go as planned is clearly a delusion. Once you start executing, you will see how rapid your plan will change.</p><p>Your pitch-deck should show that you’re able to plan for short- and mid-term, analyze the current situation and build your product without completely losing focus.</p><p>The goal of the pitch-deck is not to have a step-by-step plan for your<br>product/company for the next 12 months but rather to show a potential investor that you thought about:</p><ul><li><strong>product/market fit</strong></li><li><strong>your market</strong> - more often than not you’ll start in a certain location and will later expand your product to the bigger market</li><li><strong>growth potential</strong> - how and where are you planning to grow</li><li><strong>competition</strong> - who’s your competitors and how your product is different/better</li><li><strong>funding amount</strong> - you should know how much funding you need and what you will spend it on</li></ul><blockquote><p>Don’t forget that there’s no formula for success - but there’s one for a failure.</p></blockquote><p>I recommend to any startup founder to register at <a href="https://signal.nfx.com/">Signal</a> and create your brief. The guys at <a href="https://signal.nfx.com/">Signal</a> did a great job at providing the questions any founder should have answers to. <a href="https://signal.nfx.com/">Signal</a> also gives you the opportunity to create briefs targeted at certain investors.</p><p>So, getting inspiration from the Signal’s brief questions, let’s talk about<br>a perfect pitch-deck and what information it needs to provide:</p><ul><li><code>Business Category/Sector</code> - you have to know whether you’re<br>planning to sell you product/service to the customers or other businesses:<br><code>B2C</code>, <code>B2B</code>, <code>B2B2C</code> etc. and what is the market for you product from the technical<br>point of view: <code>FinTech</code>, <code>CleanTech</code>, <code>FoodTech</code> etc. Your product can play in<br>multiple categories</li><li><code>Current Stage of Your Company/Product</code> - Pre-Product, Pre-Revenue,<br>Post-Revenue</li><li><code>Team</code> - Crucial topic. You’ll have a lot more chances to get funding, and let’s be honest, to build your company if you have a team of like-minded<br>people working towards a common goal. To learn more about a <code>perfect team</code>,<br>head over to this article on my blog <a href="https://kostyuchenok.com/2021/09/27/perfect-startup-team/">Perfect Startup<br>Team</a></li><li><code>Your Company Brief</code> - description of your company in one sentence. Come up<br>with a plausible explanation of what your product does. Don’t use the<br>sentences like: <code>Airbnb for yachts</code> or <code>Uber for bicycles</code></li><li><code>Market</code> - how big is your market Why do you think it can get big. Ideally<br>your product will create its own market so that you can dominate it right<br>from the start</li><li><code>Business Model</code> - briefly explain how you’re planning to make money</li><li><code>Timing</code> - many products fail due to entering the market too early or too<br>late. Please, explain, why do you think now is the right time for your<br>product: technology shift, legislative shift, behavioural shift?</li><li><code>Traction</code> - if your product already has some traction, add this<br>information to your pitch-deck. Include the information about the user base<br>growth and the revenues. If you are working in a B2B area add the information<br>about the contracts closed and current and projected revenues. Even if you just<br>have an LoI signed with some prospects, mention it in your deck.</li><li><code>Founder/VC-Fit</code> - if you’re targeting a certain VC person or a fund, you<br>should convey here why you think it’s the right VC partner for your startup.</li></ul><p>What I personally find very important when I review the pitch-decks is how<br>little attention founders pay to the business and technology part of their decks.<br>They often do not know, how is their product different to their competitors or<br>how they are planning to make money.</p><p>Please also don’t forget that it always makes sense to validate your idea. You don’t have to build the complete product to do it - there’re ways to validate it either prior to building it or during your <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minimum_viable_product">MVP</a> phase.</p><p>Don’t try to create a perfect MVP and don’t spend time prematurely scaling it. You will be amazed how much load a regular tech stack can handle. Most of the startups will never achieve the scale they’re optimizing their products for.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I was setting up the Mbanq Labs accelerator in Singapore, I had a chance to talk to many founders and consult a lot of startups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What was striking to me, besides their eagerness to build their products, is how hard it was for them to clearly articulate the idea of their product in one sentence.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="startup, funding, pitch deck, deck, vc" scheme="https://kostyuchenok.com/tags/startup-funding-pitch-deck-deck-vc/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Product Please</title>
    <link href="https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2023/01/29/product-please/"/>
    <id>https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2023/01/29/product-please/</id>
    <published>2023-01-29T10:39:24.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-06T16:28:20.213Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Product is at the center of your startup. Your product is what it’s all about. When I say <code>product</code>, I don’t talk about the idea. Idea on its own is worth nothing. Ideas are <code>a dime a dozen</code> - everyone has them but not everyone is able to bring their idea to life.</p><span id="more"></span><div style="text-align: center;">  <figure>    <img width="100%" src="product-please.jpeg"/>    <figcaption>      Gates Sign in the Airport of Bangkok    </figcaption>  </figure></div><p>Execution is the key - that’s what startups are all about. If you cannot execute your idea, you won’t have a company and won’t make the world, <code>hopefully</code>, a better place.</p><p>Your product is not the heart but a brain of your startup. Without your product your company is brain-dead. Even if it looks shiny, it’s not operational.</p><p>The art of the product development is to deliver a working solution as fast as possible by keeping an eye on the big picture. Keep in mind that during the development of your product, your idea will transform as well. Don’t be too stubborn - otherwise you may get stuck and frustrated.</p><p>Products are hard, good products are even harder. They are hard to build, hard to launch and even harder to continuously improve.</p><p>Products solve problems. Good products solve hard problems. Hard problems are not easy to solve, so good products are hard to build.</p><p>According to <a href="https://svpg.com/our-team/#marty">Marty Cagan</a> - the founder of the <a href="https://svpg.com/">Silicon Valley Product Group</a> has the best definition of a successful product - the best products exist on the intersection of following qualities:</p><ul><li><strong>Valuable</strong> – Something that our customers will choose to use</li><li><strong>Usable</strong> – Easy to figure out how to use</li><li><strong>Feasible</strong> – Buildable using the technology stack and skills we have</li><li><strong>Viable</strong> – Workable for our stakeholders within our budget, legal, ethical, and reputational constraints</li></ul>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Product is at the center of your startup. Your product is what it’s all about. When I say &lt;code&gt;product&lt;/code&gt;, I don’t talk about the idea. Idea on its own is worth nothing. Ideas are &lt;code&gt;a dime a dozen&lt;/code&gt; - everyone has them but not everyone is able to bring their idea to life.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Startup Please</title>
    <link href="https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2023/01/18/startup-please/"/>
    <id>https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2023/01/18/startup-please/</id>
    <published>2023-01-18T12:53:56.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-06T16:28:20.217Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Startups are hard. Successful startups are even harder. Don’t let you tell otherwise. If it wasn’t hard, everyone would be a successful entrepreneur.</p><p>All successful startups are product oriented. All successful products are customer oriented, even if the initial customer is the entrepreneur himself.</p><span id="more"></span><div style="text-align: center;">  <figure>    <img      src="startup-please.jpg"      width="100%"      title="Mbanq Team at Mbanq Labs Hackathon in Singapore"    />    <figcaption>Mbanq Team at Mbanq Labs Hackathon in Singapore</figcaption>  </figure></div><p>Startups are all about growth, explosive growth. Once your company stops growing exponentially year on year, you cannot consider it being a startup anymore - you moved into the category of established companies or you went out of business, which is way more likely.</p><p>If you hear the word startup and think <a href="https://www.fastcompany.com/90790394/what-are-the-faang-companies">FAANG</a> and perks - you do not know anything about startups and you probably do not want to start one or work for one.</p><p>Startups are not about perks, off-sites, IPAs or gender wars. Startups are about <code>blood, sweat and tears</code>.</p><p>Startup is about constant grind, consistency and stamina. Startup is neither a sprint nor it is a marathon - startup is a <code>fartlek</code> - a long run consisting of short high-intensity intervals and short slower paced ones. Startup is about being able to fall and stand up over and over again.</p><p>If none of the above is something you can live with - do not join a startup and do not start one - you will definitely fail.</p><p>Why do people start companies then? The answer is very simple - because they cannot do otherwise. You have founders, who want to change the world and founders, who ride the current hype wave and want to make money. You have people, who cannot stand the bullshit and politics of big corporations and crazy scientists, who have been working on their idea for years and got discovered by a VC. All of them have different motivations but they have at least on thing in common - they are ready to sacrifice their time, health and their relationships to bring their idea to life.</p><p>There is no product that’s created in a vacuum. You will always have competition. The competition will be fierceful. If you want to truly make it, you have to be at the very top. Only a monopoly doesn’t compete - don’t let you tell otherwise.</p><p>All product related things aside - startups are all about grit. If you decided to build your own product and to dedicate your life to it - expect a bumpy ride. It will be probably the best decision of your life but only if you will have the right attitude.</p><p>I hope this book will help you to avoid some obstacles on your way to success. It doesn’t represent the absolute truth, it just gives you some insights that I would love to know before embarking on a startup journey. I will keep it short, I promise - I know you won’t have a lot of free time on your hands. I also won’t get very deep into the startup matter. To paraphrase Leo Tolstoy:</p><blockquote><p>All happy startups resemble one another, but each unhappy startup is unhappy in its own way</p></blockquote><p>Ok, let’s not waste any more time and concentrate on the topics that will hopefully help you to create a <code>happy</code> and successful startup - to infinity and beyond!!!</p><h1 id="On-A-Side-note"><a href="#On-A-Side-note" class="headerlink" title="On A Side-note"></a>On A Side-note</h1><p>I would like to thank everyone at Mbanq. Without the team that was carefully assembled by Mbanq’s CEO <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/lounegov" target="_blank">Vlad Lounegov</a> - I wouldn’t be able to truly experience the startup life and share with you any insights.</p><ul><li>Ideas are worth nothing without execution</li><li>Your customers do not care about your tech</li><li>Startup is a marathon not a sprint - pace yourself</li><li>Timing matters but you cannot control it</li><li>You don’t know how your product will be used</li><li>It will be harder than you think</li></ul>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Startups are hard. Successful startups are even harder. Don’t let you tell otherwise. If it wasn’t hard, everyone would be a successful entrepreneur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All successful startups are product oriented. All successful products are customer oriented, even if the initial customer is the entrepreneur himself.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="startup, book, preface, chapter" scheme="https://kostyuchenok.com/tags/startup-book-preface-chapter/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Why Startup</title>
    <link href="https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2022/11/10/why-startup/"/>
    <id>https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2022/11/10/why-startup/</id>
    <published>2022-11-10T21:04:36.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-06T16:28:20.221Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Why do people start companies? The reasons are different. Some want to get rich and famous. Some think they can do things better than the others. Some just cannot help it not to be creative.</p><p>What all the founders have in common is the <code>ignorance</code>. They do not realize yet how hard their journey will get and how many obstacles they’ll have to overcome to build their dream product.</p><p>For the founders - <code>ignorance is a bliss</code>.</p><span id="more"></span><p>Despite the reason for building a product, it can become successful but the products themselves can be quite different - take a look and <code>Windows</code> and <code>Mac OS X</code>.</p><p>Arguably the best products are built from <code>scratching one&#39;s own itch</code>. If something really bothers the founders, they will do all in their hands to relieve the pain. It’s not enough to feel the pain though, you should be able to hire the team of people who are either feel the same pain or be so good at <code>evangelizing</code> your own pain into someone else. We will talk about hiring in a later chapter.</p><p>You can take another path and jump on the current bandwagon - be it <code>web3</code>, <code>crypto</code>, <code>AI</code> or anything else that is hype at the moment. Being on the bandwagon will help you to get attention and interest from <code>VCs</code> and <code>investors</code>. Most of the investors don’t look for the startups with challenging ideas but rather prefer to invest into the proven ideas that can be scaled fast.</p><p>Building a company is hard. It may be the hardest thing you will ever attempt to do but it is also the most rewarding one. If you have the guts and if you are not afraid of failure - you should definitely grab the chance and go for it.</p><p>If you are already in the process of building your company and launching your product, continue reading further. I hope this book will help you overcome some of the obstacles that get in your way.</p><p>If you hear <code>startup</code> and the only thing you imagine is a nice office with a lot of perks and a fancy coffee machine - you will be having a hard time building a product.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Why do people start companies? The reasons are different. Some want to get rich and famous. Some think they can do things better than the others. Some just cannot help it not to be creative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What all the founders have in common is the &lt;code&gt;ignorance&lt;/code&gt;. They do not realize yet how hard their journey will get and how many obstacles they’ll have to overcome to build their dream product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the founders - &lt;code&gt;ignorance is a bliss&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="startup, book, founders, ideas" scheme="https://kostyuchenok.com/tags/startup-book-founders-ideas/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>How To VC after 2022</title>
    <link href="https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2022/08/01/vc-ing-after-2022/"/>
    <id>https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2022/08/01/vc-ing-after-2022/</id>
    <published>2022-08-01T15:51:18.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-06T16:28:20.221Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The world is changing very rapidly. Markets are crashing, money is disappearing, new unions are being created, the old ones are being destroyed.</p><p>The investments are not as they were even a year ago. VC’s didn’t get any wiser but they’ve gotten more precautious. On one hand they have to spend the money cause it’s losing its value every day, on the other hand they cannot spend it on the startups that don’t make any profit.</p><span id="more"></span><h2 id="For-VCs"><a href="#For-VCs" class="headerlink" title="For VCs"></a>For VCs</h2><p>What should the VCs do to at least try to stay on the safe side of things and not lose all their investments:</p><ul><li>Only invest in startups that are profitable as of today</li><li>Stop throwing money away by investing in copy cats that are sharing the same markets</li><li>Don’t invest in startups that are not ready to explore totally new markets</li><li>Europe won’t be a big market in the next 2-10 years - look elsewhere</li><li>The safest European countries to still invest in are Great Britain, Spain, Portugal</li><li>The least safest European countries are the Baltic States</li><li>US are still a good market to invest in</li></ul><p>A bit more on Great Britain - The Commonwealth is one of the biggest English Speaking markets worldwide and will not only stay relatively stable but will grow together even stronger, so it will be easier for startups to roll out in the new Commonwealth country and thus get more customers. Spain and Portugal will fall into the realm of Great Britain with a very high probability.</p><p>African market will stay very turbulent and unpredictable - it can yield very high profits but can also bring very high losses. The same will be true for Latin America and some parts of Asia.</p><h2 id="For-the-startups"><a href="#For-the-startups" class="headerlink" title="For the startups"></a>For the startups</h2><p>If you start a company in Germany now - start looking at other markets immediately. German market will crash very soon. Middle class will practically cease to exist - people won’t be able to pay for your product. The only thing you will be able to sell here are microloans. Even if it sounds funny to you - if you want to build product for German speakers - start your business in Austria, not Germany.</p><p>If you are a startup based in France, be prepared to expand your business to a former french colony, France will start being active in their former colonies again - they won’t have any other markets to operate in.</p><p>Spain and Portugal - it probably sounds suspicious but you are on a safer side of things. Prepare to work with the Commonwealth countries. You will have quite a market soon.</p><p>If you haven’t started to build your product yet - start looking into the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agricultural_technology">AgTech</a> space - VCs should and will start investing more and more into agriculture.</p><h2 id="Concluding-Thoughts"><a href="#Concluding-Thoughts" class="headerlink" title="Concluding Thoughts"></a>Concluding Thoughts</h2><p>The world is not going to be the same anymore. Be prepared to do more with less and open absolutely new markets for yourself.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The world is changing very rapidly. Markets are crashing, money is disappearing, new unions are being created, the old ones are being destroyed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The investments are not as they were even a year ago. VC’s didn’t get any wiser but they’ve gotten more precautious. On one hand they have to spend the money cause it’s losing its value every day, on the other hand they cannot spend it on the startups that don’t make any profit.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="vc, investment, geo-politics" scheme="https://kostyuchenok.com/tags/vc-investment-geo-politics/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Rise and Fall of DKB</title>
    <link href="https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2021/12/23/dkb/"/>
    <id>https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2021/12/23/dkb/</id>
    <published>2021-12-23T09:40:51.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-06T16:28:20.205Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As of today <a href="https://dkb.de" target="_blank">DKB</a> is the third largest direct bank in Germany with more than 3.9 million customers.</p><p>After it has introduced the custody fees for the deposits larger than 25.000 Euros and removed its best product - a fee free credit card that could be used abroad free of charge both for payments and withdrawals it’s destined to lose some of its clients.</p><span id="more"></span><p>DKB is a relatively young bank - it’s been around since 1990 and is owned by <a href="https://www.bayernlb.de/">BayernLB</a> since 1995.</p><p>It’s not a secret that DKB is BayernLB’s most valuable asset and that is responsible for the majority of <a href="https://finanz-szene.de/banking/wo-der-485-mio-e-gewinn-der-bayernlb-so-ploetzlich-herkommt/">the group revenue</a>.</p><p>All German banks are pressured by the custody fees imposed on them by the European Central Bank since 2014. Despite the fact that they had 7 years to solve this problem without pushing the fees on to the customers, most of them did nothing. Unfortunately DKB is one of those banks.</p><p>In the last year DKB lowered the fee free deposits three times and reached now 25.000 Euros per account. Additionally to that DKB decided to remove the fee free Credit Card from its offering - it’s a paid product now.</p><p>The time to remove the Credit Card that was perfect for traveling couldn’t be better for since COVID-19 outbreak we travel less than ever. It doesn’t take away the fact that an integral banking product is gone.</p><p>I’ve been a customer of DKB for more than a decade. This direct bank has been a hidden gem of the German banking landscape for a very long time.</p><p>As a person working in the FinTech industry for a quite some  time I really liked the fact that the bank have chosen the path of getting customers by offering the best possible banking product on the German market for an average customer free of charge without unnecessary bells and whistles.</p><p>It never had a fancy user interface, neither on the web nor on the mobile device. Despite the fact that DKB is trying to promote itself as a fancy FinTech bank and has been hiring developers for the last couple of years, any real improvements haven’t been made to the customer facing applications. DKB’s mobile application is still its website wrapped into the WebView.</p><p>Having the right products customers could bear with rather antiquated digital products but now since the desired products are removed, the customers are being left with the bank that has a below average offering in an old packaging that still claims to be a FinTech bank which sounds rather ridiculous now.</p><p>So, what will happen next. I assume DKB will lose at least 10% of its current customer base without acquiring new customers. Most if its clients who were using DKB as their main banking account will probably move to <a href="https://www.ing.de/">ING</a> - the largest direct bank in Germany will only get bigger. Some younger clients may move to <a href="https://n26.com/">N26</a>.</p><p>Unfortunately most of the new banks didn’t learn how to make money, so the only way they are able to stay afloat is to go with the subscription model without offering a great product. Accumulating a lot of money they cannot do anything valuable with it.</p><p>I would love to talk to the decision makers at DKB to understand their mid- and long term growth plans and how they’re planning to overcome the future challenges without losing most of their client base.</p><p>If you have worked or still work at DKB and would like to talk - drop me a line at <a href="mailto:igor.kostyuchenok@gmail.com">igor.kostyuchenok@gmail.com</a>.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As of today &lt;a href=&quot;https://dkb.de&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;DKB&lt;/a&gt; is the third largest direct bank in Germany with more than 3.9 million customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After it has introduced the custody fees for the deposits larger than 25.000 Euros and removed its best product - a fee free credit card that could be used abroad free of charge both for payments and withdrawals it’s destined to lose some of its clients.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Perfect Pitch-Deck</title>
    <link href="https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2021/12/10/pitch-deck/"/>
    <id>https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2021/12/10/pitch-deck/</id>
    <published>2021-12-10T15:12:22.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-06T16:28:20.213Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Startups are all about the speed of execution and iteration. If you don’t have enough financial resources to hire a team to execute on your idea 24/7 for the next 3-6 months, your best bet is to find like-minded people and start working on your pitch-deck.</p><span id="more"></span><p>Do not see your pitch-deck as <code>a means to an end</code> but rather as en exercise that you will have to do every couple of months to review your product and its position on the market. You’re doing this work primarily for yourself and not for a potential investor. You need it more than anyone else.</p><p>It’s not about you having a detailed execution plan, cause assuming that<br>everything will go as planned is clearly a delusion. Once you start executing, you will see how rapid your plan will change..</p><p>Your pitch-deck should show that you’re able to plan for short- and mid-term, analyze the current situation and build your product without completely losing focus.</p><p>The goal of the pitch-deck is not to have a step-by-step plan for your<br>product/company for the next 12 months but rather to show a potential investor that you thought about:</p><ul><li><strong>product/market fit</strong></li><li><strong>your market</strong> - more often than not you’ll start in a certain location and will later expand your product to the bigger market</li><li><strong>growth potential</strong> - how and where are you planning to grow</li><li><strong>competition</strong> - who’s your competitors and how your product is different/better</li><li><strong>funding amount</strong> - you should know how much funding you need and what you will spend it on</li></ul><blockquote><p>Don’t forget that there’s no formula for success - but there’s one for failure.</p></blockquote><p>I recommend to any startup founder to register at <a href="https://signal.nfx.com/">Signal</a> and create your brief. The guys at <a href="https://signal.nfx.com/">Signal</a> did a great job at providing the questions any founder should have answers to. <a href="https://signal.nfx.com/">Signal</a> also gives you the opportunity to create briefs targeted at certain investors.</p><p>So, getting inspiration from the Signal’s brief questions, let’s talk about<br>a perfect pitch-deck and what information it needs to provide:</p><ul><li><strong>Business Category/Sector</strong> - you have to know whether you’re<br>planning to sell you product/service to the customers or other businesses:<br>B2C, B2B, B2B2C etc. and what is the market for you product from the technical<br>point of view: FinTech, CleanTech, FoodTech etc. Your product can play in<br>multiple categories</li><li><strong>Current Stage of Your Company/Product</strong> - Pre-Product, Pre-Revenue,<br>Post-Revenue</li><li><strong>Team</strong> - Crucial topic. You’ll have a lot more chances to get funding, and<br>let’s be honest, to build your company if you have a team of like-minded<br>people working towards a common goal. To learn more about a <strong>perfect team</strong>,<br>head over to this article on my blog <a href="https://kostyuchenok.com/2021/09/27/perfect-startup-team/">Perfect Startup<br>Team</a></li><li><strong>Your Company Brief</strong> - description of your company in one sentence. Come up<br>with a plausible explanation of what your product does. Don’t use the<br>sentences like: <code>Airbnb for yachts</code> or <code>Uber for bicycles</code></li><li><strong>Market</strong> - how big is your market Why do you think it can get big. Ideally<br>your product will create its own market so that you can dominate it right<br>from the start</li><li><strong>Business Model</strong> - briefly explain how you’re planning to make money</li><li><strong>Timing</strong> - many products fail due to entering the market too early or too<br>late. Please, explain, why do you think now is the right time for your<br>product: technology shift, legislative shift, behavioural shift?</li><li><strong>Traction</strong> - if your product already has some traction, add this<br>information to your pitch-deck. Include the information about the user base<br>growth and the revenues. If you are working in a B2B area add the information<br>about the contracts closed and current and projected revenues. Even if you just<br>have an LoI signed with some prospects, mention it in your deck.</li><li><strong>Founder/VC-Fit</strong> - if you’re targeting a certain VC person or a fund, you<br>should convey here why you think it’s the right VC partner for your startup.</li></ul><p>What I personally find very important when I review the pitch-decks is how<br>little attention founders pay to the business and technology part of their decks.<br>They often do not know, how is their product different to their competitors or<br>how they’re planning to make money.</p><p>Please also don’t forget that it always makes sense to validate your idea. You<br>don’t have to build the complete product to do it - there’re ways to validate<br>it either prior to building it or during your <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minimum_viable_product">MVP</a> phase.</p><p>Don’t try to create a perfect MVP and don’t spend time prematurely scaling it. You<br>will be amazed how much load a regular tech stack can handle. Most of the<br>startups will never achieve the scale they’re optimizing their products for.</p><p>If you want your pitch-deck reviewed or need an advice on starting to build the<br>product - drop me a line at <ahref="mailto:igor@kostyuchenok.com"><a href="mailto:&#x69;&#x67;&#111;&#x72;&#64;&#107;&#x6f;&#115;&#x74;&#x79;&#117;&#x63;&#x68;&#101;&#110;&#111;&#107;&#x2e;&#99;&#x6f;&#109;">&#x69;&#x67;&#111;&#x72;&#64;&#107;&#x6f;&#115;&#x74;&#x79;&#117;&#x63;&#x68;&#101;&#110;&#111;&#107;&#x2e;&#99;&#x6f;&#109;</a></a></p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Startups are all about the speed of execution and iteration. If you don’t have enough financial resources to hire a team to execute on your idea 24/7 for the next 3-6 months, your best bet is to find like-minded people and start working on your pitch-deck.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="team" scheme="https://kostyuchenok.com/tags/team/"/>
    
    <category term="startup" scheme="https://kostyuchenok.com/tags/startup/"/>
    
    <category term="pitch-deck" scheme="https://kostyuchenok.com/tags/pitch-deck/"/>
    
    <category term="product" scheme="https://kostyuchenok.com/tags/product/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Good Leaders</title>
    <link href="https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2021/10/15/good-leaders/"/>
    <id>https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2021/10/15/good-leaders/</id>
    <published>2021-10-15T10:46:38.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-06T16:28:20.209Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Everything written below is highly influenced by my personal experience and talks that were given by the people I’m following.</p><p>What you will read here is my take on the leadership.</p><span id="more"></span><h1 id="Protect-Your-Team"><a href="#Protect-Your-Team" class="headerlink" title="Protect Your Team"></a>Protect Your Team</h1><p>A good leader always protects his team from other teams and other leaders (higher management).</p><ul><li>A failure of your team is your failure</li><li>A success of your team is their success</li></ul><h1 id="Support-Your-Team"><a href="#Support-Your-Team" class="headerlink" title="Support Your Team"></a>Support Your Team</h1><p>What to do when one of your teammates decided to leave - support her, even if it’s hard for you. When you see that people cannot grow further in your company or in their position, if you cannot give them the chance to grow - support them, even encourage them to leave. You’ll get a loyal person in another company/team.</p><h1 id="Loyalty"><a href="#Loyalty" class="headerlink" title="Loyalty"></a>Loyalty</h1><p>Don’t expect people to be loyal to your brand. People should be loyal to the team they belong to, not to the brand.</p><h1 id="Same-Values"><a href="#Same-Values" class="headerlink" title="Same Values"></a>Same Values</h1><p>The team and the leader should share the same values. Whenever you hire a new team member you should find out what she is ready for and what she’s not.<br>Try to hire people, not robots. The people who leave the workplace at 6pm sharp regardless of the current situation at work are as bad as the ones who put work before their kids or family.</p><h1 id="Behavioral-Patterns"><a href="#Behavioral-Patterns" class="headerlink" title="Behavioral Patterns"></a>Behavioral Patterns</h1><p>People don’t change. They also behave the same at work as they do with their family. See how your teammates behave. If your teammate treats his family badly the same will happen at work. Don’t kid yourself.</p><h1 id="Inspiration"><a href="#Inspiration" class="headerlink" title="Inspiration"></a>Inspiration</h1><p>You cannot inspire people. Your goal should be to hire inspired people. If you hire the ones who love what they do, they’ll already be inspired by themselves. The best thing you can do is to to not kill their inspiration.<br>Communicate honestly with them. They should know why do you think they shouldn’t do certain things. But bear in mind if you already tried something and failed it doesn’t necessarily mean it won’t work next time with different people.</p><h1 id="Let-Them-Make-Mistakes"><a href="#Let-Them-Make-Mistakes" class="headerlink" title="Let Them Make Mistakes"></a>Let Them Make Mistakes</h1><p>You have to let them make their own mistakes. Mistakes are the best source of learning - that’s just a nature of learing. If you make all the decisions for them they won’t grow and will leave sooner rather than later. If you let them make their own mistakes they will grow faster by order of magnitude.</p><h1 id="Let-Them-Show-Off"><a href="#Let-Them-Show-Off" class="headerlink" title="Let Them Show Off"></a>Let Them Show Off</h1><p>Let your people the chance to show their accomplishments. If you see a team where only the leader is known for the work done, it means he is afraid of growing people stronger than him. A leader has to be sure that when he quit there are two people who can take his place and work better than him.</p><h1 id="Listen"><a href="#Listen" class="headerlink" title="Listen"></a>Listen</h1><p>Whenever you have to make a decision, hear everyone’s opinion before you announce your own. If you announce your opinion/solution first and hear a better one afterwards, it might get hard for you to accept it. It can lead to an irrational decision just because your pride didn’t let you take someone else’s opinion before yours.</p><h1 id="Gossip"><a href="#Gossip" class="headerlink" title="Gossip"></a>Gossip</h1><p>Don’t allow or participate in any gossip inside of your team - it will tear your team apart. Even worse, when you have a confrontation between two strong personalities inside of your team - you’ll have to fire at least one of them.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Everything written below is highly influenced by my personal experience and talks that were given by the people I’m following.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What you will read here is my take on the leadership.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="team" scheme="https://kostyuchenok.com/tags/team/"/>
    
    <category term="dynamics" scheme="https://kostyuchenok.com/tags/dynamics/"/>
    
    <category term="leaders" scheme="https://kostyuchenok.com/tags/leaders/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Add shortcuts to your PWA</title>
    <link href="https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2021/10/10/pwa-shortcuts/"/>
    <id>https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2021/10/10/pwa-shortcuts/</id>
    <published>2021-10-10T10:43:18.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-06T16:28:20.213Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Although the end of PWAs has been proclaimed a while ago, the Progressive Web Apps keep getting better.</p><p>Not only the processors have been improving at a rapid rate but also the<br><a href="https://nodesource.com/blog/why-the-new-v8-is-so-damn-fast/">V8 is getting better</a> with every iteration.</p><span id="more"></span><p>So, if you don’t have time to build your mobile app with React Native, Flutter or going full native with Swift or Kotlin - PWA can still be a good low entry barrier option.</p><p>The addition of <a href="https://web.dev/maskable-icon/">maskable icons</a> let your app finally have a more appealing icon that will be placed on the screen of your mobile phone if you decide to <code>install</code> it.</p><p>If you would like to try out the maskable icons, check out the <a href="https://maskable.app/">Maskable<br>App</a> - it allows you to easily create maskable icons for your app.</p><p>What can make your app even more appealing and can make it feel even more<br><code>native</code>-like are the shortcuts.</p><p>Shortcuts are accessible through long press on phones and right-clicking on desktop. When a user does a long press, he will see a context menu with links to a certain action of your app.</p><p>Let’s imagine you build a banking app and you want your users to be able to quickly access the <strong>Transfer Money</strong> screen that’s available under <code>https://my-shiny-bank.io/send-money</code></p><p>In order to add this shortcut to your PWA, you have to add the <code>shortcuts</code><br>section to your <code>manifest.json</code> file:</p><figure class="highlight json"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br><span class="line">9</span><br><span class="line">10</span><br><span class="line">11</span><br><span class="line">12</span><br><span class="line">13</span><br><span class="line">14</span><br><span class="line">15</span><br><span class="line">16</span><br><span class="line">17</span><br><span class="line">18</span><br><span class="line">19</span><br><span class="line">20</span><br><span class="line">21</span><br><span class="line">22</span><br><span class="line">23</span><br><span class="line">24</span><br><span class="line">25</span><br><span class="line">26</span><br><span class="line">27</span><br><span class="line">28</span><br><span class="line">29</span><br><span class="line">30</span><br><span class="line">31</span><br><span class="line">32</span><br><span class="line">33</span><br><span class="line">34</span><br><span class="line">35</span><br><span class="line">36</span><br><span class="line">37</span><br><span class="line">38</span><br><span class="line">39</span><br><span class="line">40</span><br><span class="line">41</span><br><span class="line">42</span><br><span class="line">43</span><br><span class="line">44</span><br><span class="line">45</span><br><span class="line">46</span><br><span class="line">47</span><br><span class="line">48</span><br><span class="line">49</span><br><span class="line">50</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line">&#123;</span><br><span class="line">  <span class="attr">&quot;name&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;BANG&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">  <span class="attr">&quot;short_name&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;BANG&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">  <span class="attr">&quot;description&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;Neo Bang&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">  <span class="attr">&quot;start_url&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;/&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">  <span class="attr">&quot;display&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;standalone&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">  <span class="attr">&quot;orientation&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;portrait&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">  <span class="attr">&quot;background_color&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;#1B252C&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">  <span class="attr">&quot;theme_color&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;#1B252C&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">  <span class="attr">&quot;icons&quot;</span>: [</span><br><span class="line">    &#123;</span><br><span class="line">      <span class="attr">&quot;src&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;/icons/bang-maskable-192.png&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">      <span class="attr">&quot;sizes&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;192x192&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">      <span class="attr">&quot;type&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;image/png&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">      <span class="attr">&quot;purpose&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;maskable any&quot;</span></span><br><span class="line">    &#125;,</span><br><span class="line">    &#123;</span><br><span class="line">      <span class="attr">&quot;src&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;/icons/bang-maskable-512.png&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">      <span class="attr">&quot;sizes&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;512x512&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">      <span class="attr">&quot;type&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;image/png&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">      <span class="attr">&quot;purpose&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;maskable any&quot;</span></span><br><span class="line">    &#125;</span><br><span class="line">  ],</span><br><span class="line">  <span class="attr">&quot;shortcuts&quot;</span>: [</span><br><span class="line">    &#123;</span><br><span class="line">      <span class="attr">&quot;name&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;Transfer&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">      <span class="attr">&quot;short_name&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;Dough Disposal&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">      <span class="attr">&quot;description&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;Send some dough to your peeps&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">      <span class="attr">&quot;url&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;/send-money&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">      <span class="attr">&quot;icons&quot;</span>: [</span><br><span class="line">        &#123;</span><br><span class="line">          <span class="attr">&quot;src&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;/img/shortcuts/black/send-money-4x.png&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">          <span class="attr">&quot;sizes&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;96x96&quot;</span></span><br><span class="line">        &#125;</span><br><span class="line">      ]</span><br><span class="line">    &#125;,</span><br><span class="line">    &#123;</span><br><span class="line">      <span class="attr">&quot;name&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;Overview&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">      <span class="attr">&quot;short_name&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;My Dough&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">      <span class="attr">&quot;description&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;Where is my money?&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">      <span class="attr">&quot;url&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;/overview&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">      <span class="attr">&quot;icons&quot;</span>: [</span><br><span class="line">        &#123;</span><br><span class="line">          <span class="attr">&quot;src&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;/img/shortcuts/black/overview-4x.png&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">          <span class="attr">&quot;sizes&quot;</span>: <span class="string">&quot;96x96&quot;</span></span><br><span class="line">        &#125;</span><br><span class="line">      ]</span><br><span class="line">    &#125;</span><br><span class="line">  ]</span><br><span class="line">&#125;</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>Once you added the shortcuts section, the icons you would like to see in your contextual menu and redeployed your app, you should get a result similar to the following:</p><div style="text-align: center;">  <img src="screenshot.jpg" width="50%" /></div><p>If your app functionality is hidden behind the authentication don’t forget to add the redirection to the shortcuts <code>&quot;url&quot;: &quot;/send-money&quot;</code> after a successful authentication.</p><p>The good design should be predictable - so, if your shortcuts represent the menu points of your app, then you should use the same icons both for your shortcuts and in your menu.</p><p>If you’re using material design library for your product you can download<br>material design icons: <a href="https://github.com/material-icons/material-icons-png">here</a> or <a href="https://www.materialpalette.com/icons">here</a></p><p>If you use <a href="https://fontawesome.com/">Font Awesome</a> you can use this Font <a href="https://fa2png.app/">Awesome 2 PNG</a> converter.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Although the end of PWAs has been proclaimed a while ago, the Progressive Web Apps keep getting better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only the processors have been improving at a rapid rate but also the&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nodesource.com/blog/why-the-new-v8-is-so-damn-fast/&quot;&gt;V8 is getting better&lt;/a&gt; with every iteration.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Perfect Startup Team</title>
    <link href="https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2021/09/27/perfect-startup-team/"/>
    <id>https://kostyuchenok.com/blog/2021/09/27/perfect-startup-team/</id>
    <published>2021-09-27T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-06T16:28:20.213Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you’re long enough in the tech business, you should have heard a tale about 3H that every startup needs. In order for a startup to become successful it needs 3 founders:</p><ul><li>a Hacker</li><li>a Hustler</li><li>a Hippie (they call it Hipster nowadays but don’t follow the crowd)</li></ul><p>If you think about this setup for a bit, this constellation will definitely start making sense.</p><p>Let’s see what every one of those <code>3H</code> actually entails.</p><span id="more"></span><h3 id="A-Hacker"><a href="#A-Hacker" class="headerlink" title="A Hacker"></a>A Hacker</h3><p>Let’s start with the easiest one. A Hacker is your CTO - someone who will build the product, someone who cares about building cool products, someone who understands how to spend time efficiently.</p><p>Some tend to spend too much time over optimizing the early stage product.<br>Scalability doesn’t matter when you didn’t find your product fit yet. When you over optimize too early in the process, you’re wasting at least double the time by not executing on your idea, losing time on unnecessary bells and whistles before having found your product market fit.</p><p>As you may know, startup is all about the execution. The faster you can execute, the higher are the chances of your startup to become successful.</p><p>So a hacker should know how to <code>cut corners</code> in a smart way. There is a huge difference between your <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minimum_viable_product">MVP</a> and your end product.</p><p>Building products is hard, building valuable products is even harder - that’s exactly why every <code>hacker</code> needs a counterpart - <code>a hippie</code>.</p><h3 id="A-Hippie"><a href="#A-Hippie" class="headerlink" title="A Hippie"></a>A Hippie</h3><p>Who’s a hippie you may ask. If you are too young and don’t know who <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Jobs">Steve<br>Jobs</a> was, I pity you and recommend you to start getting to know about him.</p><p>Up to this date, I personally consider him to be the best <code>product person</code><br>ever - you can argue, I don’t care.</p><p>So, if you haven’t seen <a href="https://vimeo.com/475108226">The Lost Interview</a> yet - do it now, you won’t regret it.</p><p>One of the questions Steve was asked is <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uf6TzOHO_dk">Are you a hippie or a nerd</a> - so when the best <code>product person</code> of all time considered himself <code>a hippie</code>, we can assume that <code>a hippie</code> is your <code>CPO</code>.</p><p><a href="https://svpg.com/our-team/#marty">Marty Cagan</a> - the founder of the <a href="https://svpg.com/">Silicon Valley Product Group</a> has the best definition of a successful product - it emerges on the intersection of following three properties:</p><ul><li><code>Valuable</code> - Something that our customers will choose to use</li><li><code>Usable</code> - Easy to figure out how to use</li><li><code>Feasible</code> - Buildable using the technology stack and skills we have</li></ul><p>The best products exist on the intersection of those three qualities.</p><h3 id="A-Hustler"><a href="#A-Hustler" class="headerlink" title="A Hustler"></a>A Hustler</h3><p>This one is almost as clear as <code>a hacker</code> position. Your hustler is your <code>Head of Sales</code>. A very important person on your team. Don’t be disillusioned - <a href="https://samuelmullen.com/articles/startup-fallacies-if-you-build-it-they-will-come/">build it and they will come</a> is a fallacy. In the world full of similar products and never ending competition, you need <code>a hustler</code> who will sell your product to your customers and your idea to the investors.</p><p>This is the person who knows and believes in your product and help <code>a hippie</code> to find the best possible <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Product/market_fit">Product/market fit</a>.</p><h3 id="On-A-Side-note"><a href="#On-A-Side-note" class="headerlink" title="On A Side-note"></a>On A Side-note</h3><ul><li>Ideas are worth nothing without execution</li><li>Your customers do not care about your tech</li><li>Startup is a marathon not a sprint - pace yourself</li><li>Timing matters but you cannot control it</li><li>You don’t know how your product will be used</li><li>It will be harder than you think</li></ul>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you’re long enough in the tech business, you should have heard a tale about 3H that every startup needs. In order for a startup to become successful it needs 3 founders:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a Hacker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a Hustler&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a Hippie (they call it Hipster nowadays but don’t follow the crowd)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you think about this setup for a bit, this constellation will definitely start making sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s see what every one of those &lt;code&gt;3H&lt;/code&gt; actually entails.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
